<?xml version="1.0"?>


<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
]>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-dmlloyd-sasl-public-key-01" category="std">
    <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

    <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
    <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
    <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
    <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
    <?rfc strict="yes" ?>

    <front>
        <title>SASL Public Key Authentication (PK)</title>
        <author initials="D.M." surname="Lloyd" fullname="David M. Lloyd">
            <organization>Red Hat, Inc.</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>100 East Davie Street</street>
                    <city>Raleigh</city>
                    <region>NC</region>
                    <code>27601</code>
                    <country>US</country>
                </postal>
                <phone>+1 919 754 4950</phone>
                <email>david.lloyd@redhat.com</email>
                <uri>http://redhat.com/</uri>
            </address>
        </author>

        <date month="January" year="2016"/>

        <area>Security</area>

        <keyword>RFC</keyword>
        <keyword>Request for Comments</keyword>
        <keyword>I-D</keyword>
        <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
        <keyword>SASL</keyword>
        <keyword>Public Key</keyword>

        <abstract>
            <t>Thanks to the success of the Secure Shell (SSH; <eref target="rfc4251"/>), the usage of public key
            authentication as a more secure alternative to password-based authentication is widespread on the Internet today.
            Unfortunately, to date there is no standard way to reuse these existing types of credentials in most other protocols.</t>
            <t>This specification describes a family of Simple Authentication and Security Layer (SASL; <eref target="rfc4422"/>)
            authentication mechanisms which uses public/private key pairs to authenticate a user, including those
            currently in use for the purposes of SSH authentication.</t>
        </abstract>
    </front>
    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction">
            <t>This specification describes a family of authentication mechanisms for performing public key authentication
            which provides a simple alternative to password-based authentication strategies.</t>
            <t>This family of mechanisms does not include negotiation of a security layer.  It is intended for use with
            an external security layer (optionally using channel binding [see RFC 5056]).</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Conventions Used in This Document">
            <t>RFC 5234 stuff</t>
            <section title="Terminology">

            </section>
            <section title="Notation">

            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="PK Algorithm Overview">
            <t>
                The PK client is in possession of a user name and a private key. The user name is sent to the server with
                a public key, along with a client-generated nonce. The server retrieves the user information and
                compares the
                public key to the server's stored key.
            </t>
            <t>
                The server then sends a challenge to the client including a server
                nonce and the server's public key. The client compares the server public key to a locally stored key for
                that host.
            </t>
            <t>
                The client then sends a message to the server consisting of a cryptographic signature produced
                by the user's private key over the channel binding data (if any) and the first client and server
                messages.
            </t>
            <t>
                The server replies with a cryptographic signature produced by the host's private key over the same data
                plus the client's signature message.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="PK Mechanism Names">

        </section>
        <section title="PK Authentication Exchange">

        </section>
        <section title="Channel Binding">

        </section>
        <section title="Formal Syntax">

        </section>
        <section title="PK as a GSS-API Mechanism">

        </section>
        <section title="Security Considerations">

        </section>
        <section title="IANA Considerations">

        </section>
        <section title="Acknowledgements">

        </section>
    </middle>
    <back>
        <section title="Design Motivations">

        </section>
    </back>
</rfc>